<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>karanjakhar.net - Blog</title><link href="https://karanjakhar.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://karanjakhar.net/feeds/blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://karanjakhar.net/</id><updated>2024-03-11T10:20:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Ideal state fallacy</title><link href="https://karanjakhar.net/ideal-state-fallacy.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-03-11T10:20:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-03-11T10:20:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Karan Jakhar</name></author><id>tag:karanjakhar.net,2024-03-11:/ideal-state-fallacy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The ideal time to take an action never arrives. The utopian state is unachievable. We are never fully prepared. But that’s okay.&lt;br&gt;
We usually start with chaos, and as we go further, we bring order to it, but the perfect order stays unachievable.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Two types of ideal state expectation …&lt;/h3&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The ideal time to take an action never arrives. The utopian state is unachievable. We are never fully prepared. But that’s okay.&lt;br&gt;
We usually start with chaos, and as we go further, we bring order to it, but the perfect order stays unachievable.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Two types of ideal state expectation traps:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Preconditions&lt;/strong&gt; - The ideal state to take action:&lt;br&gt;
The ideal state for starting something new rarely exists.&lt;br&gt;
Let's start by recalling an event that happened a few days back:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a vegetable called bitter gourd which grows on vines. It has different varieties, one of them is very small in size—a bit larger than berries. We had a few vines of those small ones scattered in our fields. One day my uncle was picking those and asked me why I never picked those from the vines. He wondered if I didn’t like them. I told him I like them, but I don’t pick them because I feel I won’t find enough for one meal. Perhaps I’ll pick them in a few days when more of them grow.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said, &lt;em&gt;“Once you start picking, you’ll keep finding more, and soon there will be enough. You just need to start. It might take longer than you imagine, but you will eventually have enough.”&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized how often we do that—looking for a perfect time to start something.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideal state to start learning a new skill is unachievable. The perfect state to start writing or reading will never arrive. The conditions to start a business will never be perfect. The preconditions are often just excuses we make to delay taking action.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we do that? Because we fail to acknowledge that we have a finite amount of time here on earth and think that we can do everything we want. But that's just a way of closing our eyes to reality. There will always be things for which we won’t have enough time. But that's just how it is. We have to prioritize and take action.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Perfectionism&lt;/strong&gt; - The ideal state to finish and deliver something:&lt;br&gt;
Perfectionism is a lack of courage and fear of judgment in disguise.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often believe that we should deliver a product only when it reaches perfection, but the fact is, no product will ever attain perfection. The reason why we chase this perfection is that we are scared of the unknown, uncertainty, and most importantly, others judging us. That is why a work-in-progress phase gives us the pleasure of working on something important while also saving us from the humiliation (imaginary as it may be) of delivering an imperfect product.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The efficiency of an internal combustion engine is approximately 30%. Imagine if the people who were building the first IC engine had insisted on waiting until they achieved 100% efficiency before installing the engines in cars. Guess what? We wouldn’t have had cars until now, and we wouldn’t have them in the near future either.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Air resistance is not negligible; we cannot ignore real-life friction, whether in physics problems or in life.&lt;br&gt;
Thermodynamically, achieving absolute zero is impossible; it’s simply a fundamental aspect of reality.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Solution:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
If it is a new thing for which you feel you don’t have enough time, start taking small actions. Squeeze the new activity in regardless, and it will make time for itself. As Parkinson’s law states, &lt;em&gt;“Work expands to fill the time allotted for its completion.”&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There might be activities in our day that don’t need as much time, and if given less time, they will still finish with optimum results. Accept that this life is what we have, and it is finite—you will be gone soon. Why don’t we play the most magnificent game while we are here? Do what’s meaningful?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Courage:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Just do it. Publish the article you’ve been holding on to. Start the business you’ve been wanting to. Accept that you won’t be perfect in the first iteration. A lot of the time, if you increase the quantity, your quality also improves.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, making one perfect video on YouTube is hard, but making a lot of good videos helps you improve and make the perfect one eventually. The same goes for any other activity. Don’t let the pursuit of perfection paralyze your progress; take action, learn from your experiences, and keep moving forward.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s just agree that the first few iterations of anything will suck. I have been delaying blogging for years, and still, my first blog is not near perfect. But now I have taken the step of delivering a bit less than a perfect blog, learning from the mistakes, and improving.  &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category></entry><entry><title>It takes courage, but...</title><link href="https://karanjakhar.net/it-takes-courage-but.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-03-11T00:28:31+05:30</published><updated>2024-03-11T00:28:31+05:30</updated><author><name>Karan Jakhar</name></author><id>tag:karanjakhar.net,2024-03-11:/it-takes-courage-but.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We might look at someone and think that they are doing wrong things, yet they seem happier and more fulfilled. Meanwhile, we do nothing wrong, yet we feel miserable.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this thought ever comes to your mind, then you are mistaken—not only in your judgment but also in lacking …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We might look at someone and think that they are doing wrong things, yet they seem happier and more fulfilled. Meanwhile, we do nothing wrong, yet we feel miserable.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this thought ever comes to your mind, then you are mistaken—not only in your judgment but also in lacking the courage to act wrongly.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That “bad” person at least had the courage to take risks. They took action, and now they reap the rewards. Courage is always rewarded—that’s just how it works.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you find the fruits of wrongdoing tempting, yet justify your inaction as virtue, then you are not only wrong but also weak.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no morality in simply not doing wrong. Being harmless does not mean you are good—it just means you are weak. If given power, you might misuse it. True goodness comes from strength: having the power to do wrong but choosing not to. And this is far more fulfilling than enjoying the short-lived rewards of wrongdoing.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes courage to do bad things, but it takes even more courage to do the right thing.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should never envy those who seem successful through "wrong ways." Instead, we should pity them for their weakness, even as we acknowledge their willingness to take risks.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right path is hard—there is no doubt about that. That’s why so few people take it.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So ask yourself: Are you truly good, or is your goodness just weakness in disguise?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Duality of Mind</title><link href="https://karanjakhar.net/duality-of-mind.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-21T00:19:32+05:30</published><updated>2023-08-21T00:19:32+05:30</updated><author><name>Karan Jakhar</name></author><id>tag:karanjakhar.net,2023-08-21:/duality-of-mind.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The inner voice is a dialogue - not a monologue.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
One side urges you to do something (be it good or bad), and the other finds a reason not to do it. Evaluation of the pros and cons of an activity is done by two separate thought processes.&lt;br&gt;
One voice is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The inner voice is a dialogue - not a monologue.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
One side urges you to do something (be it good or bad), and the other finds a reason not to do it. Evaluation of the pros and cons of an activity is done by two separate thought processes.&lt;br&gt;
One voice is of the ambitious, disciplined version of you—the one that sets an alarm to wake up early, that takes resolutions to quit smoking, drinking, and sugary or fried foods.&lt;br&gt;
The other voice is the lazy version—that procrastinates, eats bad food, and makes you victimize yourself.&lt;br&gt;
To take control, or to be disciplined, is to listen to the former one and follow through.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time we procrastinate on what we had planned to do or eat what we shouldn't, we feed this second voice until it gets loud enough that we stop hearing the first voice. That's the point when depression starts. At least from personal experience, every time I get indulged in a time-wasting activity, I know beforehand that this is not good for me—a voice always keeps saying, &lt;em&gt;"Don't do it, don't do it,"&lt;/em&gt; but I still do it. Not always, but a lot of the time. These little failures accumulate every day. Self-love soon becomes self-sabotage.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little successes also accumulate. You start building confidence in your abilities, and the journey gets easier. But the only caveat is that we have to do it every single day.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being disciplined doesn't mean you always feel like doing the right thing, but to have the wisdom to know what is right and follow through.&lt;br&gt;
Clarity is the precondition to discipline. When you are clear about your goals, you start separating things that will push you towards your goal from the ones that push you away from it. Then you start doing the right things, despite how you feel, and this is what discipline is.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine how great life would be if we just listened to the right inner voice consistently.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's what I do to reinforce the right behavior and reduce friction for doing hard (and meaningful) things:&lt;br&gt;
1. I try to refuse the urge to do a lazy thing at least a few times a day. Let's say I get an urge to pull out my phone and scroll Instagram. Then I notice that, tell myself this is not the right thing to do, and I don't do it.&lt;br&gt;
2. I feel like doing a challenging or weird thing, but then the second inner voice says, &lt;em&gt;"Are you mad?"&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;"Who does that?"&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;"Maybe tomorrow."&lt;/em&gt; Well, at this point, I know the inner coward doesn't want to do it. Guess what—I do it. That reinforces the correct behavior. Next time, doing the exact same thing will have less friction because I'll have evidence that backs the fact that I am capable of doing challenging things.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Referring to an old story I read somewhere: The inner voices—good and bad—are like two wolves fighting. Who wins?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one you choose to feed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category></entry><entry><title>The Illusion of Empty Sacrifices: Stop Mimicking Idols the Wrong Way</title><link href="https://karanjakhar.net/the-illusion-of-empty-sacrifices-stop-mimicking-idols-the-wrong-way.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-21T00:19:32+05:30</published><updated>2023-08-21T00:19:32+05:30</updated><author><name>Karan Jakhar</name></author><id>tag:karanjakhar.net,2023-08-21:/the-illusion-of-empty-sacrifices-stop-mimicking-idols-the-wrong-way.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The Truth About Sacrifice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacrifices are often glorified as the hallmark of success. We admire our idols for their relentless focus and willingness to give up short-term pleasures for long-term achievements. But in chasing this ideal, many of us fall into the trap of empty sacrifices—sacrificing without a clear …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The Truth About Sacrifice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacrifices are often glorified as the hallmark of success. We admire our idols for their relentless focus and willingness to give up short-term pleasures for long-term achievements. But in chasing this ideal, many of us fall into the trap of empty sacrifices—sacrificing without a clear goal, mistaking deprivation for discipline. We try to reverse the process by sacrificing first and expecting that this sacrifice itself will bring meaning.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Don't Copy the Effect, Copy the Cause&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too often, we mimic the superficial aspects of our idols' lives without understanding the deeper reasons behind their actions. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;"I don’t have time to take a trip because my idol doesn’t take trips."&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;"I don’t spend time with friends because my idol works hard in solitude."&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here’s the truth: Your idol isn’t avoiding trips or friendships to appear busy—they’re doing so because they are laser-focused on a specific goal. Their sacrifices are purposeful, not performative. Are you as focused as they are? Or are you simply playing a role, hoping that by mimicking their sacrifices, you’ll magically become productive?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Danger of Empty Sacrifices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empty sacrifices are a form of self-deception. You convince yourself that by giving something up, you’re making progress, even when there’s no real goal or action behind it. Worse, these sacrifices can lead to unnecessary sadness and regret.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You avoid activities that bring joy, thinking that suffering alone will somehow lead to success.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You forgo spending time with loved ones, not because you’re busy building something meaningful, but because you want to &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; busy.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of behavior fools you into believing you’ve done something productive. In reality, you’ve only succeeded in making yourself miserable.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sacrifice for the Right Reasons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacrifices have meaning only when they serve a purpose. They are a trade-off, not an empty gesture. To make sacrifices worthwhile:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify a Goal&lt;/strong&gt; – Before giving something up, ask yourself, &lt;em&gt;Why am I doing this?&lt;/em&gt; What am I working toward?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start Working First&lt;/strong&gt; – Don’t make sacrifices expecting them to spark motivation. Begin with action. Once you’re committed to a goal, sacrifices will feel natural and necessary, not forced.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enjoy Life’s Moments&lt;/strong&gt; – Time is limited. Don’t waste it on performative sacrifices. Spend time with friends, take that trip, or enjoy a simple pleasure—unless there’s a genuinely compelling reason not to.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Regret Teaches Us What Matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have done this multiple times because I thought sacrificing would make me more disciplined, more like the idols I admired. Now, I see how hollow that decision was. Sacrificing without purpose cost me more than I gained.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sacrifice with Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m all for sacrifice. In fact, I believe it’s one of the most powerful tools for achieving greatness. But over time, I’ve learned that sacrifice should always have a purpose. It should be a conscious decision to give up something lesser for something greater, not an aimless act of self-denial.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purposeful sacrifice brings clarity, fulfillment, and progress. Empty sacrifice only brings frustration and regret. To achieve something great, you have to be willing to make sacrifices. But those sacrifices must align with your ultimate goal.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True sacrifice isn’t about deprivation for its own sake. It’s about giving up something lesser to gain something greater. Stop mimicking your idols’ sacrifices without understanding their goals. Find your own purpose, and let your sacrifices stem from that. Only then will they have meaning—and only then will you avoid the loneliness and regret of empty sacrifices.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work hard and enjoy the limited time you have. Take a chill pill.  &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Finite vs Infinite Games</title><link href="https://karanjakhar.net/finite-vs-infinite-games.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-07-10T01:27:22+05:30</published><updated>2023-07-10T01:27:22+05:30</updated><author><name>Karan Jakhar</name></author><id>tag:karanjakhar.net,2023-07-10:/finite-vs-infinite-games.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Life is a game, and how we choose to interpret it defines pretty much everything. The game of life can be interpreted as finite or infinite.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Finite games&lt;/strong&gt; are those that have fixed rules, boundaries, and time constraints where once the whistle blows, the game is over. You either win …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Life is a game, and how we choose to interpret it defines pretty much everything. The game of life can be interpreted as finite or infinite.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Finite games&lt;/strong&gt; are those that have fixed rules, boundaries, and time constraints where once the whistle blows, the game is over. You either win or lose. The attempt to win a finite game is to fixate on the end result.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infinite games&lt;/strong&gt; are those that don’t have fixed rules, boundaries are only imagined, and there are no time constraints (except the eternal truth which is death). There is no predefined concept of winning or losing in infinite games, so you play to learn, grow, and experience. You define success and failure, and if observed carefully, you never fail.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All meaningful things in life are infinite games where there is no end goal/state that you will ever achieve. The goalpost is always moving, and striving for the goal is what adds meaning.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;You don’t want to get healthy, you want to stay healthy and fit&lt;br&gt;
You don’t want to become a good person, you want to be a good person.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infinite games are tied to a person’s identity.&lt;br&gt;
As James Clear has clearly (&lt;em&gt;xD&lt;/em&gt;) explained in his book &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Your current behaviors are simply a reflection of your current identity. What you do now is a mirror image of the type of person you believe that you are (either consciously or subconsciously).”  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Layers of behavior change" src="https://jamesclear.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Layers-of-behavior-change.png"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Playing the infinite game is the reason why Warren Buffet is still working even though he has billions of dollars. It’s not the numbers in the financial reports that add meaning to his life but the process of investing smartly. This is what adds meaning to his life more than anything. That’s the same relationship between Ronaldo and football. This is deeply embedded in their identities that make them enjoy playing the game more than the outcome.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be argued that infinite games are made up of a number of finite games, and it is true for a lot of cases. But how we interpret the motivation to play is what makes the difference. Finite games are played to win, to prove something, and to compete. Infinite games are played to keep playing, to explore, and to create. They are not mutually exclusive, but they require a different mindset and attitude.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category></entry></feed>